<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en-GB">

   <title>HXA7241 latest</title>
   <updated>2016-12-11T00:00:00Z</updated>
   <id>http://www.hxa.name/hxa7241-latest.xml</id>

   <author>
      <name>Harrison Ainsworth / HXA7241</name>
   </author>
   <link rel="alternate" href="http://www.hxa.name/"/>
   <link rel="self" href="http://www.hxa.name/hxa7241-latest.xml"/>

   <subtitle>A log of the latest additions and changes to the site.</subtitle>
   <icon>./favicon.ico</icon>
   <logo>./style/hxa7241logo_sml.png</logo>
   <rights>Creative Commons BY-SA 3.0 License</rights>


   <entry>
      <title>Why blockchain is uninteresting [note]</title>
      <updated>2016-12-11T11:10:00Z</updated>
      <id>tag:hxa.name,2016:log/2016-12-11T11:10:00Z</id>
      <author>
         <name>Harrison Ainsworth / HXA7241</name>
      </author>
      <rights>Creative Commons BY-SA 3.0 License</rights>
      <summary>Bitcoin is like a steam-powered horseshoe, or an electronic typewriter: it is a contrafunctory overlap of two different eras. It distracts from inventing new info-tech and solving manifest problems.</summary>
      <link rel="alternate" href="http://www.hxa.name/notes/note-hxa7241-20161211T1110Z.html"/>
      <content type="text">
Bitcoin/blockchain/etc is new tech stuck in an old mindset facing old problems -- digitising money and contract. In an informational world we should take the opportunity to rethink the forms of our interactions. But nothing in the elements of blockchain fosters new coherent/collective behaviour, because blockchain is at base individual-focused.

What are crypto-ledgers fundamentally? They are about unique/inimitable data-source identity (that is what is produced by their implementation: virtually-unique token + one-way function). This makes an instant, very simple consensus: if there is only one of something it is impossible, objectively, for it not to be agreed on. (What is agreement? Not merely sameness: it must have some objective anchor, or how do you know if you *are* agreeing?). Crypto-ledgers do not create new kinds of consensus, only a new form of record of any consensus. They instigate no new patterns.

The main info problem of cooperation is creating new kinds of rules/patterns -- constraints on action (-- and today, automations of them). Yet there seems nothing in crypto-ledgers that automates finding of, or induces following of, new common/shared structures. Because they perfom no abstraction: no gathering or filtering or merging of info; nor do they embody any new single fixed such abstraction. To support a shared structure, you need to coalesce info, and crypto-ledgers do not.

Reinventing money and contracts is socio-technological regress, it has all been done long ago. And the claims made of its 'decentralisation'? -- they are only a confusion of implementation with usage. The largest force of centralisation in practice is money and property, because property and money work by concentrating control in human decision. Bitcoin/blockchain etc is just a reinforcement, a digital re-invigoration, of all that -- making it run on distributed computers is immaterial to the consequence at large.

So put aside crypto-ledger stuff ... **How should we shape our local transactions with more kinds of global information? Make tech for *that* **!

--

Related:
* "What is hard in economic calculation?"; HXA7241; 2016 / note. http://www.hxa.name/notes/note-hxa7241-20161030T1229Z.html
* "A brief argument against price signals"; HXA7241; 2016 / note. http://www.hxa.name/notes/note-hxa7241-20160717T0915Z.html
* "The internet is an engine of centralisation"; HXA7241; 2015 / note. http://www.hxa.name/notes/note-hxa7241-20150920T1002Z.html
      </content>
   </entry>

   <entry>
      <title>What is hard in economic calculation?</title>
      <updated>2016-10-30T12:29:00Z</updated>
      <id>tag:hxa.name,2016:log/2016-10-30T12:29:00Z</id>
      <author>
         <name>Harrison Ainsworth / HXA7241</name>
      </author>
      <rights>Creative Commons BY-SA 3.0 License</rights>
      <summary>The reason a computationally planned, or rather assisted, economy is currently infeasible is because we lack sufficient AI capability for general 'similarity-finding' (similizesis). It is not, as commonly opined, that the required calculation or communication is intractable.</summary>
      <link rel="alternate" href="http://www.hxa.name/notes/note-hxa7241-20161030T1229Z.html"/>
   </entry>

   <entry>
      <title>Basic proglang naming schemes</title>
      <updated>2016-07-24T11:27:00Z</updated>
      <id>tag:hxa.name,2016:log/2016-07-24T11:27:00Z</id>
      <author>
         <name>Harrison Ainsworth / HXA7241</name>
      </author>
      <rights>Creative Commons BY-SA 3.0 License</rights>
      <summary>Programming languages can be classified into two well-known naming schemes (tacit, and non-), but from there one can see a third -- naming from intrinsic structure -- which seems interesting and underexplored.</summary>
      <link rel="alternate" href="http://www.hxa.name/notes/note-hxa7241-20160724T1127Z.html"/>
   </entry>

   <entry>
      <title>A brief argument against price signals</title>
      <updated>2016-07-17T09:15:00Z</updated>
      <id>tag:hxa.name,2016:log/2016-07-17T09:15:00Z</id>
      <author>
         <name>Harrison Ainsworth / HXA7241</name>
      </author>
      <rights>Creative Commons BY-SA 3.0 License</rights>
      <summary>Cooperative systems must be ambivalent, therefore they must be multi-dimensional. Prices are only unidimensional, therefore price-systems alone must be inadequate.</summary>
      <link rel="alternate" href="http://www.hxa.name/notes/note-hxa7241-20160717T0915Z.html"/>
   </entry>

</feed>
